Inventory of the Ellsworth Y. Dougherty papers, 1934-1962
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Ellsworth Y. Dougherty papers
1934-1962
Dougherty, Ellsworth Y.
03111
2.70 cubic feet (6 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Reports and maps of a mining engineer who worked primarily in the western United States.
Biography of Ellsworth Y. Dougherty
Ellsworth Y. Dougherty, a mining engineer and geologist, worked for a number of mining companies in the United States and Canada from 1911-1941. From 1941-1947 he was a mining engineer with the U.S. Bureau of Mines and from 1948-1962 was a mining engineer with the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission for its San Francisco and Seattle offices.
Scope and Content
Collection is chiefly files related to Dougherty's mine examination work in the western U.S. for the Bureau of Mines and the Securities and Exchange Commission. There is a small amount of material related to his work for private companies and clients.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Ellsworth Y. Dougherty at the date of processing.
Additional Information
Finding aid available in repository.
Acquisition Information
The collection was received from Ellsworth Y. Dougherty in 1969.
Access Terms
United States. Bureau of Mines.; United States. Securities and Exchange Commission.; Mine examination -- West (U.S.); Mine examination -- Canada.; Geology, Economic -- West (U.S.); Geology, Economic -- Canada.;; Maps.; Cross sections.; Mining engineers.; Geologists.
Agriculture and Natural Resources; Mines and Mineral Resources; Science, Technology and Health; Technology; Politics, Government, and Law
Container List
- Series I. Reports and Other Writings of E.Y. Dougherty
  - Mineral Resources of the United States, 1948, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Mineral Specimens - Illustrations and Photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - National Mineral Policy Proposal, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Professional Record and Publications List, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Reports:
    - Alunite Summary, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Barite, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Diaspore and Aluminous Minerals, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Fluorspar Summary, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Illinois-Kentucky Fluorspar District, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Magnetic Surveying in North Central Minnesota, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Moss Mine (Arizona), 1940 (Box 1)
    - Problems of the Lake Superior Iron Ore Region, 1945 (Box 1)
    - Quicksilver (Mercury) Summary, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Summary on Talc-Soapstone-Pyrophyllite, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Vidette Mine (British Columbia), 1939 (Box 1)
    - Volcanic Ash, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Wartime Developments and Postwar Prospects of the Mineral Industry of South Dakota, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Reprints:
    - Geologic Problems of the Canadian Pre-Cambrian Gold-Fields, 1935 (Box 1)
    - Mining Geology of the Vipond Gold Mine, Porcupine District, Ontario, 1934 (Box 1)
    - Ribbon Structure in Gold-Quartz Veins, 1950 (Box 1)
    - Some Geological Features of Kolar, Porcupine and Kirkland Lake (includes photographs), 1939 (Box 1)
    - Some Observations in Ore Search - Symposium (includes comments by Dougherty), 1940 (Box 1)
  - Securities and Exchange Commission Mine Investigations, San Francisco Office:
    Arranged alphabetically by mine or company name. Includes Arizona, southern California, Nevada.
    - A, 1948-1962 (Box 2)
    - B, 1948-1962 (Box 2)
    - C-E, 1948-1962 (Box 2)
    - F-H, 1948-1962 (Box 2)
    - I-K, 1948-1962 (Box 2)
    - L-M, 1948-1962 (Box 2)
    - N-O, 1948-1962 (Box 2)
    - P-R, 1948-1962 (Box 2)
    - S-T, 1948-1962 (Box 3)
    - U-Z, 1948-1962 (Box 3)
  - Securities and Exchange Commission Mine Investigations, Seattle Office:
    Arranged alphabetically by mine or company name. Includes northern California, Idaho, Montana, Oregon, Washington.
    - A-F, 1948-1962 (Box 3)
    - Benton Mine (Oregon), 1948 (Box 3)
    - G-Z, 1948-1962 (Box 3)
    - Idaho-Maryland Mines Corp., 1952 (Box 3)
- Series II. Maps
  - Alaska: Geologic, Geographic, Anchorage, Topographic, 1938-1957 (Box 4)
  - Arizona: Bradshaw Mountains, Congress, Grand Canyon, Kingman, Geologic, Jerome, Manganese Mines, Mt. Union, Mayer, Topographic, 1957, undated (Box 4)
  - British Columbia: Ainsworth, Big Bend, Mining Divisions, Bridge River, Cranbrook, East Kootenay, Eutsuk Lake, Geologic, Greenwood-Phoenix, Hazelton, Kootenay Lake, Lardeau, Nelson, Northern B.C., Portland Canal, Prince Rupert, Princeton, Quatsino-Nimpkish, Vancouver, Willow River, 1928, undated (Box 4)
  - California: Central Eureka, Grass Valley, Topographic, undated (Box 4)
  - Canada: Magnetic Declination, Mineral, 1932-1939 (Box 4)
  - Colorado: Cretaceous and Tertiary, Metallic Mineral, Uranium and Vandium, 1946-1955, undated (Box 4)
  - Idaho: Avery, Challis National Forest, Brunswick Mine, Sawtooth National Forest, Stratigraphic, St. Joe National Forest, 1939-1948 (Box 5)
  - Iowa: Geologic, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Montana: Mineral Resources, Beaverhead National Forest, Montana Idaho and Wyoming Topographical, Oil and Gas, National Forests, 1943-1957 (Box 5)
  - Nevada: Las Vegas, Lovelock, 1947-1954 (Box 5)
  - Oregon: Forests, Landforms, Mineral Deposits, Placer Mining, Quicksilver, 1948-1957 (Box 5)
  - United States: Aerial Mosaics, Aerial Photography, Gold, Geological, Lake Superior, Topographic, Stratigraphic, 1935-1962 (Box 5)
  - Utah: Bull Mountain, Mt. Hillers, Oil and Gas, Colorado Plateau, Geologic, Uranium, Vanadium in Colorado and Utah, 1944-1955 (Box 5)
  - Washington: Chelan, National Forest, Geological, Mining Districts, Mineral Industries, Snoqualmie National Forest, 1947, undated (Box 6)
  - Wyoming: Geological Survey Index, 1948 (Box 6)
- Series III. Printed Material
  - American Association of Petroleum Geologists, 1946 (Box 6)
  - British Columbia - Government Publications, 1940-1947 (Box 6)
  - Bureau of Mines 50th Anniversary, 1960 (Box 6)
  - Canada - Government Publications, 1922-1946 (Box 6)
  - Colorado Scientific Society Proceedings, 1935 (Box 6)
  - Geological Survey Professional Papers: Coeur d'Alene District, undated (Box 6)
  - Idaho Bureau of Mines and Geology, 1934-1939 (Box 6)
  - International Geological Congress Guidebooks, 1933 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Articles, 1936-1949 (Box 6)
  - Montana Bureau of Mines, 1948 (Box 6)
  - University of Arizona Bulletin, 1937 (Box 6)